<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The History of the late war with the Turks, during the siege of Vienna, and the great victory obtain'd against them, at the raising the siege together with an account of the underhand dealings of France in that affair ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 97 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 70 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43931</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2166A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11123</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12253893</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12253893</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57262</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43931)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57262)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 148:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The History of the late war with the Turks, during the siege of Vienna, and the great victory obtain'd against them, at the raising the siege together with an account of the underhand dealings of France in that affair ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 130 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at Cologn, and re-printed at London for H. Bonwicke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Vienna (Austria) --  History --  Siege, 1683.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57262:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57262:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HISTORY <hi>Of the late</hi> WAR <hi>with the</hi> TURKS, During the Siege of VIENNA, <hi>And the Great</hi> Victory obtain'd againſt them, at the raiſing the <hi>SIEGE. TOGETHER,</hi> With an Account of the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand dealings of <hi>FRANCE</hi> in that affair.</p>
            <p>Being the beſt and fulleſt Relation that has been yet publiſh'd.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>Cologn,</hi> and Re-printed at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> for <hi>H. Bonwicke,</hi> at the <hi>Red-Lion</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1684.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1-50" type="pages">
            <pb facs="tcp:57262:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57262:2"/>
            <head>A RELATION <hi>Of the preſent</hi> WAR WITH THE TURKS, <hi>Till the raiſing the Siege of</hi> VIENNA.</head>
            <p>THE Emperour ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected in making the Peace of <hi>Nime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guen,</hi> that <hi>France</hi> would reſt contented with the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:57262:3"/> advantages ſhe had already gain'd in the War. But he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> happy ſucceſſes only encreaſed her courage; for ſcarce had ſhe ſign'd the Treaty, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thought of breaking it. Thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dealing gave no ſmall troubl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the Emperor, who behel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> himſelf on the other ſid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> threatned by the <hi>Turks,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not truſting ſo much to his own ſtrength, as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve he could at the ſame tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> make head againſt two ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Potent Enemies, he thereupo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diſpatches Count <hi>Albert Capr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ra</hi> to the Port, with advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious offers to obtain a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuation of the Truce, which was between the two Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires, and now upon expiring<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> In the mean time the Partiſans of <hi>France</hi> took hence occaſion
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:57262:3"/> to blame his Conduct; pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing he was more willing to comply with the Infidels, than the King, though he might expect from him ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient aſſiſtance. But they took no notice at the ſame time, that <hi>France</hi> would come to no agreement: But upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions which were not only diſhonourable to the Empire, but tended alſo to the utter ruine of the Emperor. For the King of <hi>France</hi> would have approved by a Treaty all the infractions which he had made of the Peace of <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> and moreover certain pretenſions ſatisfied, which I can ſcarce forbear terming ridiculous, were I not withheld by the reſpect which is due to what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever comes from Crowned Heads.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:57262:4"/>
            <p>Howſoever, the Emperor im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiently expected ſome news from <hi>Caprara,</hi> when this Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador (deceiv'd by the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices of the Grand Viſier, who was wholly ſet upon amuſing him with hopes of peace, whilſt he thought on nothing but War,) advertized him he doubted not but to accompliſh his buſineſs; which fill'd the Emperor and the whole Court with joy.</p>
            <p>In effect, although he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly would have turn'd his Arms againſt this common Enemy of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> yet knowing the deſigns of <hi>France,</hi> which aſpir'd of late to the Empire, th'intereſt of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily made him reſpect it as an enemy far more dangerous, than the <hi>Turk</hi> could be; who
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:57262:4"/> at fartheſt expected but one place or two, whereas the other would ſwallow up the whole.</p>
            <p>A report being ſpread in the month of <hi>January,</hi> that the King of <hi>France</hi> would encamp 50 Thouſand men on the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and almoſt as many on the <hi>Saar,</hi> oblig'd the Emperor to ſecure the <hi>Rhyne.</hi> And altho' he had only words as yet from the <hi>Turks,</hi> he choſe rather to ungariſon <hi>Hungary,</hi> than ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe his Country to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion of the <hi>French.</hi> Count <hi>Mansfeld,</hi> who was with the King of <hi>France</hi> from the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, had in the mean time orders to obſerve whatſoever paſt: But that Court taking pleaſure in giving every day new fears, he could ſend no
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57262:5"/> certainer news than what were commonly reported, to wit, that the King would carry the War into <hi>Germany</hi> the next ſpring, if the Emporor gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him not whatſoever he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded.</p>
            <p>Altho' perhaps what I now mention'd, may appear diſtant enough from my ſubject, which is to relate the ſucceſs of the War, which the <hi>Turks</hi> made with the Emperor, yet will it not appear ſo to thoſe that ſhall take the pains, to conſider how neceſſary 'tis to ſhew what the Emperor had to fear on the ſide of the <hi>French,</hi> to the end he may not be blam'd for not immediately employing all his forces to repel the Infidels; neither will it be amiſs to take notice by
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57262:5"/> the way, that ſetting aſide Religion, 'twas more the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors intereſt to oppoſe this power than that of the <hi>Turks: Becauſe the Eſtabliſhment of the houſe of</hi> France, <hi>is the undoubted ruine of the houſe of</hi> Auſtria. Howſoever the Emperor ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the effect was far from the hope he had conceived from the promiſes of <hi>Caprara,</hi> cauſed new levies to be rais'd in all the hereditary Provinces, and ſollicited the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Princes to enter into a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy with him againſt this common enemy of <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi> The King of <hi>Poland</hi> made an offenſive and defenſive League with him: Several other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces promiſed to aſſiſt him, ſome with men, others with money, and in ſhort, great
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57262:6"/> preparations on all hands were made for War, ſeeing it could not be avoided. In the mean time it being known at <hi>Rome</hi> what paſſed in <hi>France,</hi> the Pope ſent a Brief to the King, wherein having given him all the qualities due to a great Prince, as indeed he is, he exhorted him to aſſiſt the Emperor, or at leaſt not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der others from doing it.</p>
            <p>In the mean time great care was taken to fortify <hi>Waag</hi> and <hi>Raab,</hi> the keeping of which were entruſted to the <hi>Hungarians;</hi> it being hoped, the ſeeing, not only their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, but likewiſe the lives of their Wives and Children were concerned, they could not but ſtoutly reſiſit th'enemy.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:57262:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Comorra</hi> and <hi>Raab,</hi> being lookt upon as the bulwarks of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> were carefully for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified: And it being ſuppoſed the enemy would not leave two places of that importance behind them, to come and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiege <hi>Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nna,</hi> there was leſs care than ought to be taken in ſtrengthening this laſt place: ſo that when the <hi>Turks</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd before it, the ditches were not ſo much as cleanſed, nor the baſtions repaired. Yet both theſe defects were amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded under the favour of the Cannon and Muskets, which kept th' Infidels from diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing the workmen. But that which facilitated the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of this, was, that the enemies not being able to bring their Cannon over the <hi>Danube,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:57262:7"/> by reaſon of <hi>Raab,</hi> and <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morra,</hi> which belong'd to the Emperor, they needed much time to draw it by land, the ways being broken in ſeveral places, which hindred them from planting them ſo ſoon as their occaſion required.</p>
            <p>To mention every thing in order, I ſhould firſt ſay, that the Emperor ſeeing the <hi>Turks</hi> had ſet up the <hi>Horſe-tayle,</hi> which is to them a ſignal of War, and moreover exerciſed ſeveral hoſtilities on the frontiers, he held a Council of War, reſolving to prevent their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns. 'Twas determin'd in this Council, that the Troops ſhould ſpeedily leave their Garriſons, and make their <hi>rendezvous</hi> a league diſtant from <hi>Presburg,</hi> to march thence
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57262:7"/> to <hi>Newhawſel,</hi> which was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be beſieged, in hope 'twould be taken before the <hi>Turks</hi> could ſuccor it.</p>
            <p>The Command of the Army was given to the Duke of <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain;</hi> for beſides the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence which the Emperor put in him, he ſhould by this means take away all cauſes of jealouſie from ſeveral others, who would not have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, had they been oblig'd to obey any one but the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors Brother-in-Law. In the mean while the Duke of <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain,</hi> who was ſick during the whole Winter, and ſcarce yet fully recovered; could not come ſo ſoon to the Army, and indeed made it a month before his arrival, which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion'd much miſchief: For
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57262:8"/> whilſt he was recovering from his ſickneſs, the Baſſa of <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſel</hi> had time to fortify the place, and to prepare himſelf for defence.</p>
            <p>The Governor of <hi>Gran,</hi> who likewiſe might fear the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors Arms, took care where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſoever he was concerned, and agreed with the Baſſa of <hi>Newhauſel</hi> to ſend him aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, if he ſhould be the firſt ſet upon, as alſo to receive the ſame from him, if <hi>Gran</hi> chanced to be firſt attackt by the <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Things being in this poſture; when the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> came to the Army, and made the review of it in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Emperor, Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and ſeveral other Princes, he cauſed it to march
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:57262:8"/> between <hi>Gran</hi> and <hi>Newhauſel,</hi> as if it had been ſtill uncertain which of theſe places he min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to attack. About ſix leagues off both theſe Cities he ſeem'd to be determin'd for <hi>Gran:</hi> For having made a detache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of 6000 horſe, he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them to march on the ſide of <hi>Gran,</hi> which made the Baſſa of <hi>Newhauſel</hi> believe that 'twas not he, whom he deſign'd. In the mean time to ſatisfie the agreement made betwixt 'em, as afore mention'd, he ſent out about 2000 men of his Garriſon, with orders to enter <hi>Gran.</hi> But as ſoon as ever he that Commanded the detachem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt of the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> knew they were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, he turn'd ſhort off to <hi>Newhauſel,</hi> which he inveſted.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:57262:9"/>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſht at the news of the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of <hi>Newhauſel</hi>'s being thus weak'ned, haſt'ned to the Town, and having fixt his Quarters, ſent a ſummons to the Governour to this effect, <hi>That he wondred at his obſtinacy in defending ſuch a place which had not half men enough to keep it;</hi> and thereupon adviſed him <hi>to come to a ſpeedy agreement, otherwiſe he would deal with him, as thoſe deſerve, who pertina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly ſtand upon a fruitleſs d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</hi> The Baſſa of <hi>Newhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel</hi> made anſwer to the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi>'s meſſenger, <hi>That he wondred what ſhould hinder him fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tting him to death at that inſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt, that he ſhould therefore ſpeedily r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>turn and tell his General, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> would ſhew him
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:57262:9"/> in a few days to whom the</hi> Grand Signor <hi>Entruſted his places.</hi> In effect, he on that day made a ſally out on our Guards, who gave place to the firſt impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuoſity of the <hi>Turks:</hi> Which gave an allarum to the whole Camp, and cauſed the cavalry to mount on Horſe-back, who beat back the Infidels. Yet did they carry away a great number of Priſoners, whoſe heads they cauſed to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately cut off.</p>
            <p>And to affright us the more, planted them along the walls of the Town, which was an object of great grief to ſeveral, who continually be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held the loſs they had ſuffered, of their brother, friend, or near kinſman. This happy ſucceſs encouraged afreſh the <hi>Turks</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:57262:10"/> to make another ſally the next morning, in which having likewiſe taken ſome Priſoners, they uſed 'em after the ſame manner as the former.</p>
            <p>This did not ſo damp the Courage of the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> as to hinder 'em from making uſe of it as a motive to revenge, and of more care for the future. Our batteries then were raiſed in a ſhort time, the trench opened, and there was never more hopes of a happier ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, when there aroſe a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port thro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ghout the whole Camp, That the Duke of <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain</hi> openly complained, that Prince <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rman</hi> of <hi>Baden,</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident of the Council of War, which was at <hi>Vienna</hi> with the Emperor, kindered neceſſaries being ſent him for the ſiege,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:57262:10"/> hoping thereby to make him loſe his reputation, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der himſelf more conſiderable. In fine, theſe reports were ſo common in the Army, that coming to the Ears of Prince <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>Baden Herman</hi>'s Nephew, he had ſome words about it with the Duke of <hi>Lorrain.</hi> And indeed 'twas well known of a long time, that Prince <hi>Herman</hi> had a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret jealouſie of the Duke and 'twas the opinion of ſeveral, that he would not have been much troubled had his undertakings prov'd ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsleſs. But in this occaſion, not only the wellfare of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, but moreover of all <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> being concerned, 'twas charitably judg'd this hatred was ſomewhat abated,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57262:11"/> if not wholly extinguiſht. But 'twas afterwards apparent how greatly ſuch as thus reaſoned were deceived, when they came to uſe the ammunition.</p>
            <p>Whilſt the Trench was well advanced, and there were great hopes for us, the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> receives an order from the Emperor, ſigned with his own hand, by which he was enjoyn'd to raiſe the ſiege, and put forces into <hi>Raab, Comorra,</hi> and <hi>Presburg.</hi> 'Tis impoſſible to relate the vexation which ſeiz'd the Duke at this Command, the whole fault of which he caſt on the Prince of <hi>Baden:</hi> But not able to diſpence with his obedience, he retir'd from the Town, and drew up his Army in Battalia, ſhewing by
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:57262:11"/> his countenance, that obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence was the only cauſe of his retreat. In fine, when he was to depart, he lodged ſome infantry in ſeveral houſes, which were about a quarter of a league diſtant from the Town, hoping in caſe he ſhould be follow'd, not only this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantry would favour his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat; but moreover, ſeeing the enemy muſt paſs near theſe houſes, thoſe whom he left behind in 'em might attack 'em in the Flank, and whilſt they were ſurpriz'd with the firſt Charge, the cavalry which was at the rereguard, ſhould turn head upon them, and eaſily defeat 'em.</p>
            <p>It cannot be ſaid, but that this order was given according to the rules of War, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:57262:12"/> all the likelihood in the world of a ſutable ſucceſs. But the raiſing of the ſiege had ſo diſcouraged the Troops, that when the Infidels appear'd, the rereguard doubled their pace, inſtead of facing about, leaving thoſe who were in the houſes without any hope of ſuccour. They defended them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as well as they could, for an hour or two, but the place being not tenable, they were forced to yield to a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter power, ſo that thoſe who eſcaped from the combat, were all made Priſoners.</p>
            <p>This did little advantage them, for the Baſſa no ſooner was entered into <hi>Newhauſel,</hi> but he cauſed their heads to be cut off, and planted on the ramparts of the Town, with
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:57262:12"/> thoſe who dyed with their Arms in their hands, as if he meant his cruelty ſhould add to his glory. The Count <hi>de Taxis,</hi> who was of one of the beſt Families in <hi>Spain,</hi> and whoſe Anceſtors have poſſeſſed time out of mind the Office of <hi>Great Maſter of the Poſts of that Kingdom,</hi> was one of thoſe miſerable victims.</p>
            <p>The Army, in the mean while held on the way to the Iſle of <hi>Schut,</hi> and as ſhe retir'd, news came of a greater miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune, than the raiſing the ſiege of <hi>Newhauſel.</hi> I mean of the Treaſon of the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> that were in the paſſage of <hi>Vaag,</hi> who inſtead of defending it, as was expected, joyned themſelves to Count <hi>Teckely,</hi> chief of the Male-contents of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:57262:13"/> 
               <hi>Hungary,</hi> after they had Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the other Troops, which were with them, for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the paſſage. I cannot expreſs, nor nobody with me, how great was the Armys con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternation at the firſt news of this miſhap. For every one imagining already to ſee the <hi>Turks</hi> at his elbow, thought of nothing but how to eſcape them; and as if they had nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Arms nor Hands to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them, they had the victory already yielded 'em without ſtriking a ſtroke. But that which augmented ſtill each ones fear, was, that of every party which was ſent out from the reſt of the Army, there return'd at moſt not above half, and generally in bad order.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:57262:13"/>
            <p>Every body took pleaſure in augmenting the Forces of the enemy. Some ſaying they were 300000 men, others 400 thouſand, and exaggera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting beyond all truth the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltes which they had exercis'd along the way. <hi>So ingenious are men when they are ſet upon it to do themſelves miſchief.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In fine, the <hi>Turks</hi> having paſt the <hi>Vaag,</hi> and poſſeſſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of all places, which are between that River and the <hi>Danube,</hi> arrived on the banks of this latter, where they built a Bridge above the <hi>Papas,</hi> over which paſſed their Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. The Cavalry with the Baggages paſſed over the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pas.</hi> But the Army being nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous, and the multitude generally retarding enterpriſes,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:57262:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:57262:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:57262:15"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:57262:15"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:57262:16"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:57262:16"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:57262:17"/> the Grand Viſier made ſeveral detachements, ſome to plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Country, others to purſue our Army, which had not yet gain'd the Iſle of <hi>Schut.</hi> Thoſe that were deſign'd for plunder, gather'd an ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble booty of all things. For nothing being leſs ſuſpected than the Treaſon of the <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garians,</hi> every one was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in his houſe, far from thinking their misfortune ſo near.</p>
            <p>All the Campain was then entirely pillag'd, and after the Infidels had ſatisfi'd their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, they glutted their cruelty in the bloud of Aged perſons. In fine, they ſet all on fire, ſparing neither houſes of Princes, nor Peaſants; nor thoſe of the Emperor, ſo
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:57262:17"/> that <hi>Luxemburg</hi> was burnt with ſeveral conſiderable Caſtles, and their vaſtations were ſooner known at <hi>Vienna,</hi> than the revolt of the <hi>Hungarians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Tartars</hi> who were em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd in the ruine of ſo many men, and ſtately Buildings; retir'd with the ſame precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation wherewith they came, fearing to be cut off in their way home; and left as many marks of cruelty in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat, as they made appear in their coming. This news, which was ſoon known by our Army, perfected our dread and conſternation. The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> could find no body, who would undertake to bring him news of the enemies mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and when he ſent out any, it ſeem'd as if he ſent
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:57262:18"/>
'em to their Graves. So great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly were they poſſeſs'd with an imagination of their force and cruelty. Yet the Army ſtill advanc'd, the Infantry at the head, the Cavalry at the tayl with the Dragoons. The Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage was on the left, and marcht ſeparately with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Regiment of Dragoons of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy,</hi> at the head of whom was the <hi>Chevalier</hi> of <hi>Savoy</hi> whoſe Father was the deceas'd Count of <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> the Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of Count <hi>Taff</hi> was alſo for the guard of theſe Baggages with the Cavalry detach'd from diverſe bodies. As we were at the bank of a River a party which the Duke o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Lorrain</hi> had ſent out brough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him word, that the enem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was not above a league off
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:57262:18"/> which oblig'd him to remain in the rereguard, to give or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that they might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd as they ought. But the fear was ſo great, that inſtead of hearing this Command, the Cavalry forſook the Infantry, and retir'd under the Cannon of <hi>Vienna.</hi> The Duke of <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain</hi> follow'd the Cavalry to make it return to its poſt, but not being able to become ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of it, he Commanded the Infantry with all ſpeed to paſs ever in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Iſle of <hi>Schut,</hi> whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h was n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> themſelves inc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſantly. W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he avantguard paſſed, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> appear'd, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ge the Regiment of <hi>Montecucali,</hi> who h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d the rereguard. The Baggage was likewiſe attackt at the ſame
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:57262:19"/> time, and the <hi>Turks</hi> found ſo little reſiſtance in the one and the other, that they promis'd themſelves to obtain an entire Victory that very day.</p>
            <p>In the mean while the <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er</hi> of <hi>Savoy,</hi> who was as I ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, engag'd in the defence of the Baggage, having rally'd ſome Dragoons, and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that were well diſpos'd, ſet himſelf to oppoſe the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. But his men having been ſoon beat back, he was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run by the <hi>Turks,</hi> and his horſe falling backwards on him, the pummel of his Saddle with the weight of his horſe cruſht him to death. The Infantry on their ſide fought under favour of the Waggons, or to ſpeak better, endeavour'd to make them a rampart againſt the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:57262:19"/> ſtroaks of the enemy. But as ſoon as ever the <hi>Turks</hi> had open'd a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſage, every one began to throw down his Arms, and take his heels, ſo that in ſhanning death, they found it nearer and more ignominious. For the <hi>Turks</hi> lighting on 'em thus diſarm'd, and without defence, kill'd them without the leaſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
            <p>In fine, after they had kill'd about 800, they fell on the Baggage, which ſaved the reſt of the Army. For whilſt they were buſied on pillaging, they which had not yet paſt over into the Iſle of <hi>Schut</hi> made haſt to get thither. We loſt near 13 or 14 hundred men in this conflict, amongſt whom were two Princes, to wit, the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:57262:20"/> 
               <hi>Chevalier</hi> of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and the Prince <hi>de Aremberg,</hi> three Counts of the Empire, and ſeveral Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers. Moreover the <hi>Turks</hi> took a great booty, whoſe value was eſteem'd at 3 hundred thouſand Crowns: For the Prince of <hi>Montecuculi</hi> loſt for his ſhare near 20 thouſand, the Prince of <hi>Baden</hi> a more conſiderable ſum, and ſeveral other Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers accordingly.</p>
            <p>But though every particular perſon had enough to lament the loſs of, yet this was the leaſt trouble, for there were other things of greater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment. The Infantry ſaw themſelves abandoned by the Cavalry, and knew not well which way to turn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> was gone after the horſe, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:57262:20"/> the news of him was expected with the greateſt impatiency. But he loſt no time, being reſolv'd to loſe his life, or bring off his Infantry. In ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, after ſome reproaches to the Cavalry, he tells 'em, <hi>the way to repair their fault, was to return to the enemy: That they need only follow him, for he hop'd by Gods aſſiſtance, how difficult ſoever the enterpriſe was, to come in a ſhort time to the end of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He was become deſperate by what had happen'd to him, and his affliction made him ſcarce known, ſo greatly was he alter'd by it. For beſides the danger, wherein all the Empire lay, (he knew that the <hi>good and bad ſucceſs of affairs were attributed only to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders,</hi>)
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:57262:21"/> he beheld his repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in great danger, had not fortune ſeconded his Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage. He marcht always for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, and having given ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary orders to avoid confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, he ſent away two men, by different ways, to advertiſe his Infantry, that he was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Turks</hi> knowing his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, made ſtrait up to him, to diſpute him the paſſage, but the Duke caſting himſelf firſt amongſt the firings of the enemy, open'd a paſſage with his Sword, having beat down before him all that oppos'd him. In fine, having re-joyn'd his Infantry, he was receiv'd with teſtimonies of eſteem, and an extraordinary joy. He ſhew'd them on his
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:57262:21"/> ſide the ſatisfaction he took in delivering them from that great danger, but amidſt theſe congratulations he learnt that the main body of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Army drew near, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon puts a great part of the Infantry into <hi>Raab, Comorra, Presburg,</hi> and withdrew with the reſt of his Cavalry near <hi>Vienna.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Emperor who had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd a fierce alarm by the ſuddain irruption of the Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, and who conſider'd that after the revolt of the <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> he could no longer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main at <hi>Vienna</hi> in ſurety, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought himſelf at the ſame time of leaving it. But firſt augmented the privileges of the Scholars, which were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready very great, and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:57262:22"/> that having receiv'd them as a recompence of their Courage which they ſhew'd heretofore againſt <hi>Solyman,</hi> when he beſieg'd the City, this ſhould be a freſh incite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to defend it with the ſame reſolution. He gave al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to the Shoomakers Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices their Freedom, who were to the number of about 1500, in caſe they took Arms, and did any thing conſiderable for the Country.</p>
            <p>In fine, having recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the City to Count <hi>Staren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg,</hi> whom he left therein Governor, he departed carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with him whatſoever he had valuable. He took the way of <hi>Lintz,</hi> accompanied with the two Empreſſes, the Princes his Children, and other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Quality.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:57262:22"/>
            <p>Every one wept at his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, and this Prince had much ado to forbear himſelf. So greatly was he afflicted to be thus conſtrain'd to abandon his people to the mercy of the Infidels. In the mean time each one endeavour'd to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him, to avoid the being expos'd to thoſe miſchiefs which they repreſented. In fine, there being not Coaches enough to carry all thoſe that offer'd 'emſelves, ſeveral Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of Quality got behind like Lacques; ſo that one might have ſeen the firſt Prince in the World, follow'd by all the flower of the <hi>German</hi> Nobility, to go as an exul a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt the ſcreeches and lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of his people, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented 'emſelves in his paſſage with ſhowr's of tears.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:57262:23"/>
            <p>Several Jeſuits, who were very ready to follow the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror for ſeveral reaſons, were gotten into a Waggon, at the ſight of whom the people turn'd their compaſſion into a juſt rage. And knowing their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidiouſneſs was the cauſe of all theſe miſeries, they fell upon 'em, and few eſcap'd their fury.</p>
            <p>The Emperor all this while marched with a countenance ſad and dejected like his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. Others kept a mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſilence, and although each had left their eſtates behind 'em, 'twas not known whether their own miſhap or that of the Prince was to be moſt lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. In fine, this march much reſembled a Funeral Pomp, when another ſpectacle en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creas'd
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:57262:23"/> the dolour and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion. For they beheld the other ſide of the <hi>Danube</hi> all in fire, and the Emperor having cauſed his Coach to ſtop, knowing not at firſt what it was, ſoon perceiv'd 'twas the <hi>Turks,</hi> who ſhew'd there new teſtimonies of their barbarous cruelty. He could not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold his tears at the ſight of a thing ſo much needing his compaſſion, and although he did all he could to refrain his grief, he could not effect it.</p>
            <p>Being arriv'd at <hi>Lintz,</hi> he ſtaid there ſome days expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the whole Court, which could not part at the ſame time with him. And every one being come near his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, he travell'd thence to <hi>Paſſaw,</hi> where he reſolv'd to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:57262:24"/> wait the events of the War. There came news every day which ſerved to accompliſh his miſery; for in effect he was inform'd from <hi>Hungary,</hi> that all places revolted from him, and that he had reaſon to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect thoſe about him of that Country, who mutter'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable things againſt his government.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Army advanc'd ſtill on the ſide of <hi>Vienna,</hi> which oblig'd the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> who could not reſiſt them, to put forces into the place, and thence to retire. He put in effectually 12000, who with the ancient Garriſon, amounted to about 15000 men, beſides the Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, Handycrafts men, and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other Inhabitants, who were able to do ſervice.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:57262:24"/>
            <p>Count <hi>Starenberg</hi> ſeeing the <hi>Turks</hi> were coming ſtrait to <hi>Vienna,</hi> aſſembl'd all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and made to 'em a ſhort diſcourſe to this effect. <hi>That b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fore the enemy blockt up the way, he was d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſirous of knowing who were for ſtaying in the Town, and who for leaving it. That they need only freely tell him, for he meant no hurt thereby to the one nor the other. Moreover as to thoſe who were for ſtaying with him, he muſt as freely diſcover his reſolutions to defend the place to the utmoſt extremity, ſo that if they had not Courage enough, to ſhare with him both the honour and danger, which muſt accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany all their actions, they would do better to depart than ſtay.</hi> At which words every one cryed out, <hi>he was ready to dye
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:57262:25"/> for his Country,</hi> and <hi>Starenberg</hi> ſeeing their forwardneſs, bid them hold up their hands as they would be faithful to God and their Emperor; at the ſame time one might have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held an infinite number of hands lifted up in the Air in ſign of fidelity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Starenberg</hi> having congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulated their forwardneſs, ſent away uſeleſs perſons out of the Town. But being about to turn the Women out, they entreated him not to do it, promiſing to work as well as the Souldiers, which ſo ſatisfi'd him, that he cauſed but few of 'em to depart. In the mean while he made an Inventory to be brought him of the muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of War, and proviſion; and found he had more corn
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:57262:25"/> than he needed, but few cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel for ſo great a Garriſon. He alſo found he had leſs powder, and other neceſſaries, and no one could tell whom to charge with this neglect, for time was not wanting whereby to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide all things: All that could be ſaid, was, that 'twas hop'd the place would be ſuccor'd before they came to want theſe things. For otherwiſe, this neglect of the Officers could not be ſufficiently blam'd, who believing the <hi>Turk</hi> dar'd never begin his Campain there, thought it ſufficient to ſtore <hi>Raab, Comorra,</hi> and <hi>Presburg,</hi> which they imagin'd lay more expos'd to danger. Yet was not this an excuſe for them, whoſe care ought to have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided againſt whatſoever might happen.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:57262:26"/>
            <p>But not to reprehend any one here, I ſhall only ſay that the <hi>Turks</hi> finding no body in the field to withſtand them, exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded their Army in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that it contain'd above 30 miles in front. They burnt thus a great deal of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and having left every where the marks of their cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, the Army attackt the Iſles which are on the <hi>Danube</hi> about <hi>Vienna,</hi> and having made 'emſelves maſters of them, they thereby took away all communication which they held with the Town.</p>
            <p>On the other hand, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which the Grand Viſier had ſent out, poſſeſs'd themſelves of ſeveral Caſtles, of which they burnt thoſe which were uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>leſs to 'em, and put in
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:57262:26"/> Garriſons in the others which might ſecure their Convoys. Yet had they left a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Troops about <hi>Raab, Comorra</hi> and <hi>Presburg,</hi> to curb thoſe Garriſons, which without this, had been likely to diſturb the forragers, and hinder thoſe who came every day to their Army, from travelling in ſurety. Count <hi>Teckely</hi> who had exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted great troubles in <hi>Hungary,</hi> where he held intelligence with all the great ones, the moſt part of which were his kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, had march'd in the mean time on the frontiers of <hi>Poland,</hi> to hinder not only the effect of the league, which I have already mention'd, which was concluded by the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> but likewiſe to poſſeſs himſelf
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:57262:27"/> of ſome Caſtles, which were neceſſary for this deſign. He took ſeveral of 'em without any trouble, becauſe the great ones of the Country, who deſir'd only ſome pretence to appear compell'd to take Arms againſt the Emperor, were very glad of this opportunity, and failing not to publiſh, they could do no otherwiſe than declare themſelves on the ſide of the ſtrongeſt, ſeeing they were forſaken by him who ought to protect them, they took part with <hi>Teckely,</hi> ſo that his Army every day conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably encreas'd. There was only one Barron of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, named <hi>Johanelli,</hi> who made reſiſtance in his Caſtle of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowits,</hi> and who oblig'd <hi>Teck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> to a formal attacking him.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:57262:27"/>
            <p>This Caſtle being ſituate on the top of a Mountain where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto 'twas difficult to bring up the Cannon, held <hi>Teckly</hi> a longer time than he could well ſpare from his affairs. For whilſt he was employ'd before that place, General <hi>Schuts,</hi> who had order to joyn the Troops of Prince <hi>Lubomirski,</hi> (then on their march from <hi>Poland</hi> in great diligence,) haſten'd to execute his orders, and effected 'em before <hi>Teckely</hi> could hinder him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Teckely</hi> enrag'd, that ſuch a place as this ſhould make him miſs ſo conſiderable an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, batter'd the Caſtle of <hi>Panowits</hi> with ſuch fury, that the Cannon having made a breach wherein might paſs 10 men a breaſt, he reſolv'd to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:57262:28"/> give a terrible aſſault. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Baron <hi>Johannelli,</hi> (whoſe Garriſon conſiſted of not above 200 men, and they people pickt up here and there, and who fought rather to ſave their goods, which they had laid up in the Caſtle, than for honour) ſent a meſſenger to <hi>Teckely,</hi> to let him know that he would ſurrender upon cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain conditions. But this Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral was ſo enrag'd, as I already mention'd, that he had made him loſe ſo much time, which he might to good purpoſe have us'd elſewhere, that he would not have granted a ſurrender upon any Terms, if the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Lords, who were ſome of 'em his own kinſmen, and ſome <hi>Johannelli</hi>'s, had not interpos'd their intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to give him his life.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:57262:28"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Teckly</hi> marching from thence encamp'd at <hi>Tokay,</hi> where un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding the Grand Viſier march'd on the ſide of <hi>Eſeck,</hi> he parted from his Camp with 2000 horſe, to meet and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr with him about what they had to do during this Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pain. The reception which the Grand Viſier gave <hi>Teckely,</hi> ſurpriz'd thoſe which accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied him, ſo great was the kindneſs ſhew'd him. But this <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Miniſter had pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate ends in doing this, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering it neceſſary to inſinuate into the minds of the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Lords there preſent, that he came rather to give them aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, than to enlarge the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions of his Maſter, which were already but too great, and of too vaſt extent. He receiv'd
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:57262:29"/> him then not as a Baron of the Country, but as him for whom his Maſter reſerv'd the Crown of <hi>Hungary,</hi> of which he was very willing to give him aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, in preſence of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Hungarians:</hi> To the end, that the news of it flying every where, might produce the effect he expected. He, in the mean time, orders him, to poſſeſs himſelf of the paſſage of <hi>Oralva,</hi> through which he expected the coming of the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him that thereon depended the ſucceſs of the promiſes which he made to him in the name of the Grand Signior.</p>
            <p>Things were in this poſture, when the Grand Viſier ſat down before <hi>Vienna.</hi> He imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately attackt the Subburb of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:57262:29"/> 
               <hi>Leopolſtad,</hi> which is ſeparated from the Town only by an Arm of the <hi>Danube,</hi> and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving made himſelf maſter of it, after a fierce diſpute on both ſides, he raiſed two Bridges on the River, the eaſier to communicate with his own Troops, who were ſcatter'd up and down, ſome in the Iſles, others in the main land. He expected in the mean while his great Ordnance, which could not arrive ſo ſoon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as I have already ſaid, they were forc'd to draw it by land, which was very tedious, eſpecially the ways being ſo uneven.</p>
            <p>In the interim, to loſe no time, the Grand Viſier ſet 'em to work at the lines of circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vallation, and contravallation,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:57262:30"/> which were all of 'em very irregular, by reaſon of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſituation of the Country, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which were yet no leſs ſtrong<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="50-100" type="pages">
            <p>For the former were Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non proof, and the latte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> defended by good redoubts which were rais'd in an equ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diſtance.</p>
            <p>'Till the lines of circumva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lation were drawn, the thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> part of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Army <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtill at <hi>Bivac,</hi> and althoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the reſt kept quiet in thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Tents, yet had they order <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be ready at the firſt comman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo that the horſes remain'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſaddled all night. The line<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> being finiſh'd, they were n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> longer guarded but by loo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bodies of men, which affo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded ſome reſt to the Army which was exceeding weary
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:57262:30"/> by continual ſtanding to their Arms, for they were not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oblig'd to frequent watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, but forc'd to keep-continually on horſeback, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to meet the Convoys, or for other exigences of War.</p>
            <p>On our ſide there was a great fault committed, for inſtead of waſting the Corn and Graſs growing in the fields, t' incommodate the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, they were both left un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toucht, which was the cauſe that the enemies Army, as nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous as it was in horſe, had no need to go far for forage.</p>
            <p>Whilſt this paſt, Count <hi>Starenberg</hi> had interrupted the work of thoſe that labour'd at the lines of contravallation, by frequent ſallies. But find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this proceeding diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:57262:31"/> to him (for their fell ſuch a multitude of <hi>Turks</hi> on his men, that they were always forc'd to give way,) he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented himſelf with firing the Cannon at 'em, which did good execution, 'till the enemy had made themſelves ſhelters. Theſe lines being finiſh'd, they opened their Trenches, placing 4000 horſe to defend the Workmen.</p>
            <p>The fire of the Town was very great all the night, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which Count <hi>Starenberg,</hi> caus'd ſeveral Artificial fires to be thrown over the Walls, to diſcover on what ſide the enemies were at work.</p>
            <p>The great Ordnance of the <hi>Turks</hi> being now arriv'd, 'twas plac'd on ſeveral Mounts, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to do Execution. The Grand
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:57262:31"/> Viſier ſet 20 thouſand men to guard it, in caſe the Chriſtians ſhould attempt to encloſe it. For an <hi>Italian,</hi> who had fled into his Camp, aſſur'd him that Count <hi>Starenberg</hi> had ſuch a deſign, and although the enterpriſe appear'd to him ſo difficult, that he could ſcarce credit it, yet was he reſolv'd to be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in no manner of precaution.</p>
            <p>He caus'd 4 batteries to be rais'd, two of which plai'd againſt one baſtion, ſo that one might ſay they were one and the ſame battery, were it not that they ruin'd it on both ſides. As to the two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, they were plac'd againſt two other works, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended the City on the ſide of the Scotch and Red Gates, where the Grand Viſier de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:57262:32"/> to make his attack.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as ever theſe bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries were finiſh'd, they were ſo well ſupply'd, that the Town receiv'd a thouſand ſhot the firſt day, and more than 16000 the two next: All the City Cannon were in theſe 3 days diſmounted, and great numbers were wounded, with ſeveral Officers kill'd in their attendance on it. This furious beginning fill'd the whole City with terrour, which was encreas'd by the <hi>Bombs,</hi> that ſet ſeveral parts on fire, and that were with great difficulty quench'd.</p>
            <p>The Citizens, who were not us'd to theſe kind of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſters, had already loſt above half their Courage, which they ſhew'd before the ſiege
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:57262:32"/> began. And Count <hi>Starenberg</hi> knowing there were not wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſome who began to talk of a ſurrender, caus'd a Gallows to be ſet up in the Market<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place; ſwearing in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of ſome of the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Citizens, that he would hang thereon the firſt that ſhould mention any ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>This ſeverity, which was not unſeaſonable, retain'd the moſt fearful in their duty and obedience. But leſt the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens ſhould infect the Soldiers with the ſame fears, he hindred, as much as in him lay all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication with 'em. And although he firſt thought to diſtribute ſome of his Soldiers amongſt the City Trained-bands, to make them the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:57262:33"/> more hardy and expert, yet he chang'd his reſolution, leſt as I now mention'd, the fear of the one, ſhould leſſen the Courage of the other.</p>
            <p>The Emperor, who was at <hi>Paſſam,</hi> as I already obſerv'd, receiv'd in the mean time meſſengers every day from the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> who inform'd him what he could of the ſiege, of which he was but indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently inform'd himſelf. For two men which Count <hi>Staren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg</hi> ſent him, were taken by the <hi>Turks,</hi> as they endeavour'd to paſs over to his Camp, and were at the ſame time hang'd, for having Letters found about 'em. He could not then know more, than what common fame brought him, which took plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to make things worſe than
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:57262:33"/> they were, every one regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the preſent, by what had paſt, which indeed was not very fortunate.</p>
            <p>The Emperor was in a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal anguiſh touching what would become of him. For on one hand the <hi>moſt Chriſtian King,</hi> having made his Troops to march toward the fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers of <hi>Germany</hi> came thither in perſon, and 'twas reported his deſigns were againſt <hi>Cologn,</hi> or <hi>Philipsburg,</hi> having Penſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, as well in one place as the other. In effect in the latter of theſe one <hi>Nigrelly</hi> was ſuſpected, and in the former the whole Town.</p>
            <p>Moreover the King of <hi>Spain</hi> was ſo dangerouſly ſick, that he was given over by his Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians; whereupon the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:57262:34"/> conſider'd in caſe he dyed, the King of <hi>France</hi> would have ſeveral claims to decide with him, and fall boldly on the Empire, which perhaps otherwiſe he durſt not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, leſt he ſhould draw on him the hatred of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Princes.</p>
            <p>Being troubled with theſe fears, he receiv'd two grateful meſſengers the one informing him the King of <hi>France</hi> was return'd home, and the other that the King of <hi>Spain</hi> was on his recovery. He wanted only to hear the ſiege of <hi>Vienna</hi> went ill on the Viſiers ſide, but was inform'd on the contrary, that the <hi>Turks</hi> every day recruited their Camp, with freſh Troops, and their endeavours grew e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:57262:34"/> moment more ſucceſsful againſt the Town: This news baniſht the joy from his heart which he had conceiv'd at the former. And forgetting not to haſten the ſuccors which he was promis'd from ſeveral parts, he ſent expreſſes into all Courts to repreſent the neceſſity he had of aſſiſtance, and to excite his Allies to a ſpeedy contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution.</p>
            <p>In the mean while the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs of <hi>Seppeville,</hi> Envoy from the King of <hi>France</hi> to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, was the perſon from whom the bad news of the ſiege was ſooner learnt than from any other. And he made it his buſineſs, to retail it out to every one, although this made him ſuſpected by the Emperor; ſeeing he diſpatcht
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:57262:35"/> four meſſages in one week to the King his Maſter. He hop'd perhaps by this means to give him a great deal of ſatisfaction, but he at the ſame time inſpir'd the Prince of <hi>Conti</hi> with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ſignalize himſelf againſt the Infidels, who was more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over diſcontented at the Kings giving to his prejudice the Government of <hi>Languedoc</hi> to the Duke of <hi>Maine,</hi> his natural Son; which had been promis'd him in eſpouſing <hi>Madamoiſelle de Blois.</hi> He communicated his deſign only to Prince <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genus</hi> of <hi>Savoy,</hi> Brother to the Chevalier of <hi>Savoy,</hi> who was kill'd in the ſervice of the Emperor, as I have already mention'd, leſt in making more acquainted with it, ſome one ſhould diſcover it to the King.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:57262:35"/>
            <p>He reſolved to part from the Court, on <hi>Monday</hi> the 25th of <hi>July,</hi> and having commanded his Coach-man to tarry for him at the Pallace Royal, where was Monſieur the Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> lately come from <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailles,</hi> he mounted on Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back with Prince <hi>Eugenus,</hi> attended only by a Page, but without a Livery, and took Poſt for the Road of <hi>Senlis.</hi> About ten miles from <hi>Paris,</hi> a Poſtillion knew him, ſo that the Prince of <hi>Conti</hi> having ſpoken to him, and the other giving him his Title, the Prince askt him whether he knew him, and the other anſwering he did, he gave him four Piſtols, not to diſcover which way he went, &amp; changing Hats with him, thought he might
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:57262:36"/> thus paſs on unknown. But this fellow had no ſooner left him, but carries the Hat to the Houſe of <hi>Conde,</hi> which he gave to <hi>Gourville</hi> intendant of Monſieur the Prince, Uncle to the Prince of <hi>Conti.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They were all till then in great trouble, for his Coach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man who had waited for him at the Pallace Royal till eleven at night, had ſet all the houſe in Alarum. And it being known, he had left the Court, this troubled Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam the Princeſs of <hi>Conte,</hi> but yet not ſo much as the King, who could not imagine what was become of him. The King had ſent word hereof to the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> who was then at <hi>Paris</hi> by the Duke of <hi>Fuiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lade,</hi> and this Prince who was
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:57262:36"/> ready to return to <hi>Chantilly,</hi> came to him, to remain aſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for his Nephews Fidelity. In the mean time thoſe that believed they knew him, ſaid he was not much troubled at this diſparition, which ſhewed the Prince of <hi>Conti</hi> had cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and could not ſuffer the Duke of <hi>Maine</hi> to be preferred before him without Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Immediately as ſoon as 'twas certain at Court what Road he had taken, the King ſent ſeveral Meſſengers after him, and gave one of them, whoſe name was <hi>Saintraillees,</hi> and belonged to the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> a Letter for him, written with his own hand, in which he called him his <hi>Son;</hi> but which at the ſame time told him, <hi>that if he return'd
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:57262:37"/> not ſpeedily, hee'd never ſee him.</hi> Whilſt 'twas doubted, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering his circumſtances, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he would obey or no, the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> ſent him Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Exchange for twenty thouſand Crowns, knowing he had carried but 600 Piſtols with him; and that his occaſions would require them if he went further. But this being an encouragement to him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue his Journey, rather than break it, gave every man oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to believe, the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> would not be much troubled ſhould he not ſhew himſelf ſo obedient.</p>
            <p>This Princes departure, to ſignalize himſelf againſt the <hi>Turks</hi> (for 'twas not doubted but 'twas his deſign) gave ample matter of diſcourſe to
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:57262:37"/> the people, ſome attributing this reſolution to the reaſon which I before related, others to a domeſtick grievance, which was muttered ſoon after his Marriage.</p>
            <p>But to return to <hi>Saintrailles,</hi> he arrived at <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſſels</hi> the ſame day he parted from <hi>Verſailles.</hi> And being informed the Prince of <hi>Conti</hi> only paſt thorow it, and had taken the road of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logn,</hi> he got to <hi>Namur,</hi> whence he came down by the <hi>Meuſe,</hi> to <hi>Liege,</hi> where he reſted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while: and taking poſt thence uſed ſuch diligence, that he overtook the Prince of <hi>Conti,</hi> who ſeeing in the Kings Letter, the threatnings he uſed, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved on obeying him, ſo that having embraced Prince <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genus,</hi> of whom the King made
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:57262:38"/> no mention, and who was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to continue his Journey, and given him a Diamond of great value, he leaſurely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned toward <hi>France,</hi> ſending <hi>Saintrailles</hi> before him, who long'd to give the King an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of his Journey. But <hi>Saintrailles</hi> found the King in ſuch a ſurprize by the Death of the Queen, who dyed in a manner ſuddenly, that he had ſcarce leaſure to think on the Prince of <hi>Conti.</hi> Yet was he well enough pleaſed at his obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, ſeeing it much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned him, that whilſt he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavored at the ruin of the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> ſhe ſhould not have a Prince of the Blood in her hands, for whom ſhe might expect a great Ranſom, ſuppoſing ſhe could not ſo
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:57262:38"/> greatly exaſperate his diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, to make him uſe his Arms againſt his Allegiance.</p>
            <p>The affairs of the Prince of <hi>Conti</hi> bearing ſome Relation to the ſubject I handle, I hope will be a ſufficient excuſe for the digreſſion. I ſhall now return to the Siege of <hi>Vienna,</hi> which the <hi>Turks</hi> continued with ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, ſometimes favourable and ſometimes contrary. <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remberg</hi> ſeeing they advanced in their works, ſtill made ſome Sallies, in one of which he had ſo briskly charged 'em, that if all their Horſe had not come into their aſſiſtance with the <hi>Janiſaries,</hi> he had made a grievous rout amongſt them and their works. But finding the match to grow unequal, he ſounded a retreat, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:57262:39"/> good order he obſerved, yet did he loſe ſeveral Officers of note, and no ſmall number of common Soldiers.</p>
            <p>Soon after this he diſcovers a dangerous enterprize, begun by two Chriſtians againſt the City, one of which was an <hi>Albanian</hi> by Nation, and the other of <hi>Candia.</hi> Their deſign was to ſet fire on ſome parts of the Town, under pretence of quenching that which often was fired by the Enemies Bombs. But there being found Straw, inſtead of water in their hands, they were apprehended, and put on the Rack, where confeſſing their crime, they were puniſhed as they deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Their heads were after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſever'd from their bodies and ſet upon the wall, not only
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:57262:39"/> that they without might know their ſecret practiſes were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, but alſo to keep thoſe within from the like Treaſons.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Army receiving no recruits, but what were brought by Camels and Waggons, did not ſo abound, but that they were often in want. Forrage more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over became thin near the Army, and therefore they were forced to go far. In this neceſſity the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi> ſent part of his Horſe on the ſide of <hi>Raab,</hi> and cauſed a party of Foot to come to the Camp, which lay on that ſide the Country, of which he had more need than of the Horſe.</p>
            <p>With this Foot which were all in breath the deſigns greatly
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:57262:40"/> advaneed. So that the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi> ſeeing himſelf no further from the Counterſcarp than ten paces, reſolved to attack it after he had ſprung a mine, in the Ruins of which he thought he might ſecurely lodge. But the mine inſtead of damnify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the beſieged, falling on the ſide of the aggreſſors, ſeveral that had advanced to be ready for the aſſault were deſtroyed in its Ruins. Whoſe places being fill'd up by others, the Counterſcarp was attackt with ſuch Vigor, that 'twas wreſted by the Swords point. But <hi>Staremberg,</hi> who conſidered that if he gave the <hi>Turks</hi> time to lodge themſelves there t'would be the loſs of the Town, ſent thither freſh men, which after a ſharp diſpute on both ſides,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:57262:40"/> drove the <hi>Turks</hi> thence, of whom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they made a great Slaughter.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Turks</hi> believing their honour was concerned to retake the Counterſcarp, and better keep it than before, blew up another Mine, which proving more effectual than the former, made one part of the work fly up into the Air, together with ſome men that were upon it. Which daunting the Chriſtians courage, ſeveral began to faint and give way, whilſt the <hi>Jani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries</hi> aſſiſted by the Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, poſſeſt themſelves of the Counterſcarp. They began at the ſame time to entrench them ſelves, when <hi>Staremberg</hi> haſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Men's aſſiſtance en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavored to hinder 'em, and with his Sword in his hand
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:57262:41"/> vigorouſly attackt them, min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling ſeveral Granadiers with his Soldiers, in whom he had plac'd his chief confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Janiſaries</hi> although they had not time to ſhelter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, yet fail'd not to receive him bravely, and having like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe advanc'd their Granadiers, and being poſſeſs'd of the higher ground, they ſcarcely fir'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Granado which had not its effect: the heat of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians inſenſibly abated, and <hi>Starenberg</hi> perceiving they gave ground, bethought himſelf of a retreat, plainly perceiving all his endeavours would be fruitleſs.</p>
            <p>In effect, <hi>Starenberg</hi> having made the Counterſcarp on the ſide of the City to be Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-min'd,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:57262:41"/> and his Mine being unperceiv'd, he had no ſooner retir'd far enough, but he blew it up, which cauſed ſeveral <hi>Turks</hi> to caper in the Air. The <hi>Turks</hi> were by this put in great diſorder, and <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renberg</hi> reſolving to make his advantage of it, return'd to the Charge before they could put themſelves in order. But a Battalion advancing to their aſſiſtance, the fight began a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain with equal heat, but with a ſucceſs very different.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Turks</hi> finding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves refreſh'd every moment, inſtead of loſing Courage, felt their forces augmenting, whilſt the Chriſtians whoſe Ranks ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd thin, as any one might ſee by half a look, began to waver. In effect that which
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:57262:42"/> they had before their eyes, was a ſpectacle terrible enough to aſtoniſh the moſt reſolute. For they could not make a ſtep, but they muſt paſs over the bodies of their Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the greateſt part of which, lying gaſping for life, were trodden to death by the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Starenberg</hi> ſeeing that inſtead of reſtoring good order a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his men, the diſorder every moment encreas'd, chang'd the deſign which he had of Re-taking the Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcarp, into that of preſerving what had yet eſcap'd the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies hands. And having made his retreat, and taken great care of the wounded, he made a review of thoſe Forces he had left him; which
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:57262:42"/> he found diminiſh'd by a third part, not ſo much by Sallies, and in this laſt occaſion, as by the Dyſentery or Flux which began to rage in the Town, as well amongſt the Citizens as Soldiers. In effect the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigues together with the bad food they eat, had ſo heated the bloud of moſt of 'em, that they fell ſick every day. And it being impoſſible for 'em af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this to do ſervice, the reſt, whoſe wearineſs en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creas'd as faſt as the number of the others diminiſh'd, were ſoon in the ſame condition, or at leaſt ſo tir'd out with la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and watching, that they were all ready to drop down as they march'd. <hi>Staren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg</hi> found himſelf ſtruck with this diſtemper, which
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:57262:43"/> caſt 'em all into a general damp, it being obvious to every one that the Town could not be defended without him. It being fear'd if he continued his inceſſant labours any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, he would fall at length under a dangerous malady, he therefore was entreated to give himſelf reſt, and thoſe of the principal Officers who ſtill enjoy'd their perfect health, offer'd the beſt of their aſſiſtance to eaſe him. But <hi>Starenberg</hi> conſidering with a great deal of reaſon, that the condition wherein things lay, requir'd a greater induſtry than his own, would therefore truſt to no body, ſo that although he was very ill, yet did he order all things, as if he had been in perfect health.</p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:57262:43"/>
            <p>In the mean time the <hi>Turks</hi> having made themſelves ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Counterſcarp, and repaired it the beſt they could, to keep it, brought up their Ordnance to it, and there planted 'em, which began to make a horrid confuſion in the Town. They beat down above 300 Foot of the Wall, with one part of the Ravelin: And <hi>Starenberg</hi> deſirous to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy both theſe inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies, cauſed a retrenchment to be drawn in the City, over againſt the Wall which the <hi>Turks</hi> had beat down. As to the Ravelin, he would have repaired it, but the enemies Cannon hinder'd him, and he was forc'd to content him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with half finiſhing it.</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:57262:44"/>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> had in this time pitch'd his Camp between <hi>Vienna</hi> and <hi>Crembs,</hi> on the other ſide the <hi>Danube,</hi> where he had a Bridge of Boats, over which he made his men paſs as oft as they had occaſion. He had ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened the head of his Bridge with two good Forts, where he had lodg'd his Cannon and Foot Soldiers; ſo that the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy willing to drive him thence, ſent out a Party to ſurpriſe <hi>Tulm,</hi> which would have made his Bridge uſeleſs, becauſe that after they had rendred themſelves maſters of the Town, they would have put therein a Garriſon, which would have ſo ſtraitly preſſed our men, that they could not extend themſelves beyond
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:57262:44"/> the <hi>Danube,</hi> as they did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving notice of this deſign, ſent word to the Governor of <hi>Tulm</hi> to beware of ſurprizes. In the mean while to prevent the Enemies return without fighting, he ſent out a Party of his men, almoſt as numerous as that of the Enemy, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both met, they ſo roughly encountered, that there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd of both ſides a great number dead in the field. Yet the advantage lay on the Chriſtians ſide, who put the <hi>Turks</hi> to flight. But they not daring to purſue 'em too far, for fear of falling into ſome ambuſh, were oblig'd to reſt contented with what they had already perform'd.</p>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:57262:45"/>
            <p>This happy ſucceſs was ſeconded by ſeveral others. For two or three Parties of our men, having met with ſeveral Troops of the Enemy, kill'd a great number of 'em, and made the reſt Priſoners of War.</p>
            <p>But this was not ſufficient, for without a ſpeedy ſuccor, <hi>Vienna</hi> was in great danger, Envoys were therefore diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patcht into all Courts, to know what withheld 'em from ſending that aſſiſtance they promis'd, and which the City ſo much needed.</p>
            <p>The Pope joyn'd not only entreaties to thoſe of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, but alſo a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Briefs, of which the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> was never ſparing, and by which he
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:57262:45"/> granted great indulgences to thoſe that ſuccor'd <hi>Vienna</hi> with Money, and an aſſurance of going ſtrait to <hi>Paradice,</hi> to ſuch as dyed in ſo juſt a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel.</p>
            <p>But he being ſenſible that all this would not ſignifie much, if he added not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto effective aſſiſtance, he therefore ſent good ſums of Money to the Emperor, part of which came from his own Coffers, and the reſt from the Cardinals, who did this not ſo much out of devotion, as to aſſure their own Fortunes, which would have been ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, had <hi>Vienna</hi> fell under the <hi>Ottoman</hi> power. The Pope likewiſe ſent <hi>Ranucci</hi> into <hi>France</hi> in quality of his <hi>Nuncio,</hi> to move that King
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:57262:46"/> to contribute to the ſuccor of <hi>Vienna.</hi> And to make him the more welcom, gave him conſecrated <hi>Agnuſſes</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from him to the Duke of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> Son to Monſieur the <hi>Dauphin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the King being not over joyful at the news of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſent an expreſs to <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nucci</hi> not to paſs beyond <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leans;</hi> under pretence that he was ſetting out himſelf for the Frontiers; for what I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late happen'd about the month of <hi>May.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the mean time the Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentery inſtead of abating in the City, every moment en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creas'd, ſo that near an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred perſons dyed every day, as well Citizens as Soldiers. As to <hi>Starenberg,</hi> if the good
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:57262:46"/> dyet he uſed, and which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers had not, contributed on one hand to his recovery, on the other, God who would not chaſtiſe the Chriſtians by the loſs of <hi>Vienna,</hi> permitted him by little and little to recover his health, that he might continue his diligence as he had begun.</p>
            <p>Yet things were ſtill in a very bad caſe, howſoever we conſider 'em. For on one ſide the Garriſon were ready to drop down with faintneſs, and on the other no comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table news came of ſuccour; beſides 'twas reported and that not without truth, that the King of <hi>Poland</hi> had about him perſons that were Penſioners of <hi>France,</hi> who endeavour'd to inſinuate, that there could
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:57262:47"/> be no ſurety to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, in making its Forces march out, whilſt there were ſuch dangerous enemies at the Gate, and ſuch as were glad of, and lay ready for ſuch an opportunity.</p>
            <p>Yet receiving news continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally from that King of his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs to march, theſe aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances balanced the contrary reports, which <hi>Starenberg</hi> took care to conceal from his Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon; for 'twas to be fear'd leſt this ill news ſhould quite emaſculate the Soldiers Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, who appear'd already but too faint, by ſo many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy events, and ſuch a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous diſtemper wherewith they were afflicted.</p>
            <p>But that which contributed to render this malady more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:57262:47"/> was the Airs being ſo infected by the ſtench of the dead Bodies which lay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buried, that it could not be more dangerous in a time of Plague. The cauſe of this ſtench was that <hi>Starenberg</hi> would not yield to any terms of a Truce propos'd by the Viſier, to take away thoſe of his party, who had been kild in ſo many ſeveral skirmiſhes, hoping that beſides the diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure he would receive there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, this would be a ſpectacle to damp the Courage of the Soldiers, when in march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up to the Charge, they ſhould ſee before their Eyes the fortune of their Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which would be a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to them of the like.</p>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:57262:48"/>
            <p>Howſoever whether 'twas this infection or ſomething elſe, which brought this grievous ſickneſs into the Town, they were ſo greatly incommodated by it, that they would willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have been deliver'd from of it at the coſt of a greater danger from the enemy. Yet did this diſtemper rage as well in the Camp of the <hi>Turks,</hi> of which there dyed every day near 300, but which was ſcarce perceva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, becauſe they continually receiv'd freſh ſupplies, which made up their loſſes. But theſe being people never train'd up in War, they ſeem'd to come there only to fill up a number, and not to encreaſe the forces of their party, and being not accuſtom'd to undergo the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigues of War, the greateſt part
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:57262:48"/> of 'em fell ſick at the end of two days, and rather encreas'd the confuſion than confidence of the Army.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Starenberg</hi> who had advice of whatſoever happen'd in their Camp, took thence occaſion to excite his people to patience, to whom he declar'd by a kind of prediction, that the coming of the King of <hi>Poland</hi> would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the ruine of the Infidels, and prove the deliverance of the City. And indeed 'twas time for him to come, now or never. For the <hi>Turks</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing advertiz'd that he was upon his march, uſed their utmoſt endeavours to become maſters of the Town; they had gain'd a Baſtion, in taking of which, they ſurpaſs'd themſelves, if one may ſo ſay.
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:57262:49"/> For although the Chriſtians had made a marvellous reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and ſuch as might be expected from perſons enſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by a noble deſpair; all this had hitherto ſerved only to ſet a greater luſter on the valour of the Enemy.</p>
            <p>The Baſtion being taken, they attackt the <hi>Ravelin</hi> before mentioned, at the taking of which continuing to Teſtify their Courage, they forced all within to leave it to 'em. But a Mine which the Chriſtians had made, being at the ſame time blown up, they found in another kind of death, that death which they deſpiſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a different figure.</p>
            <p>They attempted afterwards a deſcent into the ditch, ſet up their gabions and gallery,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:57262:49"/> and thundring at the City more than ever with their Cannon, they prepared them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to carry it by a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral aſſault, before the King of <hi>Poland</hi> could arrive. The day was ſet for ſo great a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, being the 29th of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> a day ſacred amongſt them, and which they Solemnized with a great deal of Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the <hi>Viſier</hi> careſſed the Officers to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage them the more, telling 'em the day was come to put an end to their Labors, he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted them not only to do their duty, but every one in particular to incourage his Souldiers. Theſe Officers in complyance with the command of the <hi>Viſier,</hi> called together
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:57262:50"/> their Regiments, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of viewing their Arms. And taking thence occaſion to ſpeak of the enterprize, which the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi> had formed, told them 'twas their fault the whole War was not ended in one day. That if they took <hi>Vienna,</hi> not only all the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Towns, which were in <hi>Hungary,</hi> would ſurrender of themſelves, without ſtriking a ſtroke, but a way thorow all <hi>Germany</hi> would be laid open, where there was no ſtrong City, a good and plentiful Country, and wherein every one would find a recompence of his labour. As they held with 'em this diſcourſe, the Grand <hi>Viſier,</hi> who was come out of his Tent, to Authorize by his preſence the words of
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:57262:50"/> his Commanders, appeared from one end of the line to the other, where in paſſing, he ſmiled on every one, to ſhew his approbation of what the Captains had told 'em: then he begins to order all things neceſſary for the attack. So that <hi>Staremberg</hi> fearing greatly that day, was as careful on his ſide that every one ſhould prepare himſelf to do his beſt, in ſuch an urgent Occaſion. In the mean time he burnt the Gallery which the Enemies had made in the ditch, and having thrown ſeveral Artificial fires on the Wood which they heap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therein, he ſo happily ſet it on fire, that the <hi>Turks</hi> who ran thither with all their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, could not put it out. The fire which they of the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:57262:51"/> Town made was ſo great in this rencounter, that the like was never ſeen, and as the <hi>Turks</hi> were buſied in quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fire in the Faggots, there were ſeveral of 'em kil'd, and many wounded.</p>
            <p>This happy ſucceſs rais'd up the Chriſtians courage, but did not abate that of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels, who preparing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as by a prelude for a general aſſault, came to make ſome eſſays of their forces, pretending ſometimes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>build their Gallery, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whiles to carry away the Town. And although they did not uſe all their ſtrength, yet did they ſo harraſs the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, which every day grew weaker, that the Souldiers were ſcarce able to ſtand on their Leggs.</p>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:57262:51"/>
            <p>'Twas about this time, that the Grand <hi>Signor</hi> reckoned him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſo ſure of the City, that he ſuffered Count <hi>Caprara,</hi> who had been detained by diverſe pretences, to return to the Emperor. And as this cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance may ſerve to unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive thoſe, who imagine that Empire has leſs policy than power, I ſhall mention here, under what colour he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd, and what was the real cauſe of it.</p>
            <p>The Grand <hi>Signor</hi> appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending, leſt the Chriſtians ſhould joyn together for the aſſiſtance of the Emperour, had thereupon amuſed all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long this Miniſter with ſome propoſitions of peace. But <hi>Caprara</hi> perceiving 'twas a folly to expect it, ſeeing he
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:57262:52"/> demanded no leſs than the Crown of <hi>Hungary,</hi> would have ſeveral times been gone, but they would not let him. The affair of Count <hi>Serini,</hi> whom the Emperor had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, by reaſon of the intelligence which he held with <hi>Teckely,</hi> furniſhed the Grand <hi>Signor</hi> with a pretence, (who knew not how to detain any longer this Miniſter) to tell him he muſt ſerve for an hoſtage, till he knew in what manner they uſed Count <hi>Serini,</hi> to whom he would willingly have the Emperour know he granted his Protection. Yet all theſe proceedings were only to have a perſon near him, to whom he might make propoſitions of peace, in caſe the King of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> with the other Chriſtian
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:57262:52"/> Princes, ſhould march to the ſuccour of <hi>Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nna.</hi> But the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi> ſending him word that this Prince was ſtill a great way off, and that he ſhould take the Town, before he could come to its aſſiſtance, he thereupon diſmiſt <hi>Caprara,</hi> who was not a little glad of this his Reſolution, not reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning himſelf in ſafety whilſt in the hands of this barbarous Prince, whoſe Will ſtood for Law to all thoſe under his power.</p>
            <p>Things were in this poſture, when Count <hi>Staremberg,</hi> who had found out a way for money, to acquaint th Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> with his condition, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired a ſpeedy ſuccour, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Garriſon was much weakned, and although it
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:57262:53"/> ſhewed ſtill the ſame Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet 'twas to be ſcared, their ſtrength would ſooner fail than their courage. That his ſtock of Powder would be ſoon exhauſted, as well as the Granadoes, yet he believed he had enough, if (what he had heard ſay were true) to wit, that the King of <hi>Poland</hi> was at hand. The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> anſwered <hi>Staremberg</hi> by the ſame man that brought him the Letter. Who being got ſafe into the Town, had no ſooner delivered his Letters to <hi>Staremberg,</hi> but this Governour finding they confirmed the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival of the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and that the Town would be ſoon reliev'd, imparted this good news to the Citizens and Garriſon.</p>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:57262:53"/>
            <p>Which ſo greatly encourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed both, that it gave new ſtrength to reſiſt the <hi>Turks</hi> when they ſhould come to make their grand aſſault, and the hope of being ſoon deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from danger, made them not only reſpect that which they had already been in, as a thing of ſmall conſequence, but moreover deſpiſe that wherewith they were now threatned. The Citizens de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to keep guard in the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers room, whom they would willingly have eaſed, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>Staremberg</hi> did not doubt of their good will, yet would he not truſt them with the Poſts of Conſequence, fearing, leaſt the Enemy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at that time, they would not ſtand their ground ſo firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:57262:54"/> as the Souldiers, who being of greater experience, muſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> needs be leſs fearful.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, this terrible day<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wherein the <hi>Turks</hi> were to do ſuch wonders, being come, they betook themſelves to thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Arms, at the ſound of thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Drums, Hautbois and Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets. They made ſeveral mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to make the greater ſhew of their forces, and ſtrike the City with greater fear. Which done, the Cannon which had played ever ſince break of day with more noiſe than Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ceaſed, till it began by a general diſcharge, which was the ſignal of the aſſault which they intended.</p>
            <p>At the ſame time one migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſee thoſe that were to give th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> firſt on-ſet, who were all i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:57262:54"/> battel array, at the entrance of the Trench ſeparate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves one from another to march where they were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered; ſome with Axes, others with offenſive Arms, but all with unuſual briskneſs. The aſſault laſted ſix hours, during which the Chriſtians went through great difficulties. For the Infidels were relieved con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually by freſh men, whereas the Chriſtians had no ſooner got rid of one Enemy, but they had to deal with a ſecond, which was ſucceeded by a third, and ſo on.</p>
            <p>The Citizens, whom <hi>Starem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg</hi> had put all in Arms, ſome to guard the publick places, others to ſecure diverſe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, knowing their whole fortune conſiſted in the defence
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:57262:55"/> of the Souldiers, whom they were informed were very hard put to it, deſired <hi>Staremberg</hi> they might aſſiſt them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="100-130" type="pages">
            <p>The Count ſeeing his men ready to faint under the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Enemy, was well enough pleaſed at this Offer. And ſeaſonably putting 'em in mind of their Wives and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, their Liberty and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, he ſo greatly animated them, that they preſented themſelves on the Breach with more courage than he expected. The fight which ſeem'd to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate by the fatigue of the Souldiers, began there with great bravery. The <hi>Turks</hi> who now promiſed themſelves an aſſured Victory, enraged to ſee it ſnatcht out of their hands, fought like men deſperate. But
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:57262:55"/> the Chriſtians urged by greater motives, to uſe their whole ſtrength, ſo vigorouſly repul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them, that aſſiſted by the Soldiers, who had taken breath, and the advantage, which commonly the beſieged have over the Aſſailants, they made the Infidels turn their backs, a great number of whom re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in the breach.</p>
            <p>The Grand <hi>Viſier,</hi> ſeeing on what ſide ſoever he turn'd his men, things ſucceeded ill, ſoon ſounded a retreat, leſt matters ſhould grow worſe. He with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew into his Camp mad with vexation and deſpair. For after this Tryal, wherein he had loſt above 5000 men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thoſe that were wounded, who were near the ſame num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, he fear'd, and that not
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:57262:56"/> without cauſe, his Troops ſhould mutiny againſt him. In effect, the <hi>Janiſaries</hi> who had ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered much in all the attacks, and eſpecially in this latter, demanded without ſpending any more time fruitleſly before this place, to raiſe the ſiege, adding that of 12000 which they were but ſix weeks paſt, they now could number them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves but ſix, and thoſe ſo weakned, that they were not in condition to undertake any thing.</p>
            <p>This beginning of a ſedition was a greater affliction to the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi> than the ill ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs which he came now from having in his enterprize, and it greatly concerning him to ſtifle it in its birth, he made uſe of the <hi>Aga,</hi> which is the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:57262:56"/> name of him that commands them, and obtained from them at his interceſſion, to keep within bounds of their duty, in conſideration of a certain ſum of Money which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd them: a remedy ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily uſed to appeaſe their diſcontents, but which inſtead of effecting this, commonly, makes it ſpring up again on the firſt occaſion.</p>
            <p>The Grand <hi>Viſier</hi> was no ſooner freed from this trouble, but he fell into another. For he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orm'd that the King of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oland,</hi> having been too hard for <hi>Teckely</hi>'s vigilancy, marcht at a great rate to the ſuccor of <hi>Vienna,</hi> and that his Avantguard was already ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd on the banks of the <hi>Danube,</hi> to which he would
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:57262:57"/> joyn himſelf in a few days.</p>
            <p>At this news he cauſed the wounded and ſick to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried out of the Camp, and having added thereunto new fortifications, he bethought of reducing the Town, before the <hi>Poles</hi> came to attack him, which could not be yet, their Army being tired by a long march, and needed reſt.</p>
            <p>Several other Princes had joyn'd in perſon with their Troops the Army of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, as the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Saxony.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides there came from all parts of Chriſtendom, <hi>France</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, a great number of Lords and Perſons of Quality to the Emperors Army. All which was likely to raiſe the ſiege, without any longer ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:57262:57"/> the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> ſuppoſing he had tarried any time. But theſe two Princes being unwilling to obey the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and he being as unwilling to yield to them the command, all theſe great forces lay uſeleſs, till the King of <hi>Poland</hi> ſhould come to make them agree. For they began already to look upon one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with an ill Eye, not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering, that their buſineſs was not to contend for prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence, but for the ſafety of Chriſtendom.</p>
            <p>As for the Marquiſs of <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denbeurg,</hi> he had for ſome time flattered the Emperour with ſending him a conſiderable ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, but being urg'd to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form what he had promis'd, and hindred by the Alliance of
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:57262:58"/> 
               <hi>France,</hi> he ſought a pretence to break his word, which he found in the demand of the Dutchy of <hi>Brieg, Lignits,</hi> and <hi>Wolnaw,</hi> over which he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended a lawful Right. And truly the Emperor was reduced to ſuch an extremity, that 'twas thought he would grant him his demands rather than be without his aſſiſtance. But what the Marquiſs of <hi>Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</hi> did, being only for a fair pretence to diſengage himſelf, he thereupon adds another de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, which he knew the Emperor would never grant him. To wit, to permit the Proteſtants of <hi>Sileſia</hi> to have the free exerciſe of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, whereupon the Emperor plainly perceiving whence this dealing came, waited no more on his promiſes.</p>
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:57262:58"/>
            <p>Count <hi>Waldec,</hi> who was declar'd Prince of the Empire, very lately, and who had Command of the Circular Troops given him, came like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe into the Emperors Army, who by reaſon of his experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the War, and Zeal to his ſervice, was willing to confer with him about the manner of ſaving <hi>Vienna.</hi> The Emperor approv'd of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he offer'd him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, but expecting the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> who was to decide the whole matter, this advice and that of ſeveral others, on the ſame ſubject, ſerv'd only to content him at that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for the whole order of it was chang'd as ſoon as ever that Prince was come.</p>
            <pb n="108" facs="tcp:57262:59"/>
            <p>In fine, he arriv'd at <hi>Holbron,</hi> on the ſecond of <hi>September,</hi> with the braveſt Cavalry the World ever ſaw, but ſo tir'd, that 'twould be to hazard all, to attempt any thing in the Condition they were in. The Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> who had taken care to ſtore up Proviſion, for the refreſhment of this Army againſt it came, went to meet him at <hi>Holbron,</hi> where the King of <hi>Poland</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd him with great Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of Friendſhip and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, although they had been both rivals in the purſuit of the Crown of <hi>Poland.</hi> The Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> came thither alſo to ſalute him, and the King of <hi>Poland</hi> preſented them his Eldeſt Son, named <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:57262:59"/> a Prince of about 17 or 18 years of Age, who came to make his Apprentiſhip in the War, under the King his Father, who knew enough to inſtruct him. The former Compliments being ended, they held a Council of War, not to know whether they ſhould ſuccor <hi>Vienna,</hi> for that matter was reſolv'd upon long before, but to reſolve of the manner of doing it.</p>
            <p>The whole affair being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd by 'em, 'twas com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to the Emperor, who having approv'd of what was offer'd, it only now lay upon 'em to diſpoſe of things neceſſary for ſo great a deſign, and the Campain being not only waſted, but not ſo much as an inhabitant left in any of
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:57262:60"/> the houſes, from whom might be expected the leaſt matter, every man was forc'd to carry proviſion as well for his Horſe as for himſelf.</p>
            <p>The Grand Viſier not being ignorant of the great prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations which the Chriſtians made againſt him, took all poſſible care on his ſide to make a good defence. Yet was he in no ſmall inquietude how to effect this. For he was at variance with the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Officers of his Army, who were of opinion that without delaying 'till the Chriſtians came, they ſhould retire to <hi>Newhauſel,</hi> alledging to juſtifie the ſoundneſs of their advice, that their Army was ſo tired with this long ſiege, that the Soldiers had more need of reſt
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:57262:60"/> than labour. And moreover that the greateſt part of their men had never ſeen any thing more of War, than what this ſiege had ſhew'd 'em, how then could they reſiſt an Army, which conſiſted of the flower of Chriſtendom, and wherein moreover there were ſuch a great number of Princes and perſons of eſteem, who came there to Conquer or to Dye. That there would be no like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyhood of ſucceſs in expoſing the remainder of an unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Army, againſt ſo flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing a one, and againſt a Garriſon, whoſe valour they had ſufficiently experienc'd by the defeat of their beſt Troops, and ſo many aſſaults in vain. That whilſt they had time, they ſhould ſave not only the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:57262:61"/> Army, but alſo the reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Grand Signior, which was ſufficiently leſſen'd, by ſo fruitleſs a ſiege, and wherein they had loſt above 30 thouſand men.</p>
            <p>The Grand Viſier anſwer'd to this, that the reputation of the <hi>Sultan</hi> would rather be loſt, if after their remaining ſo long before a Town, where they had conſum'd ſo much Money, they ſhould be ſo baſe as to retire before they had ſtruck a ſtroak. That their Army was twice as big as that of the Chriſtians, and that if the Soldiers wanted expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, 'twas enough their Leaders did not, ſeeing 'twas neceſſary to the former only to have Courage, and theſe to have skill. That the <hi>Turks</hi>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:57262:61"/> ſhould keep their ground, which was all that could be deſired of a Soldier. That as to ſucceſs, that indeed was uncertain, but howſoever they could not fail of this conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of having done their duty, and not having fled from the Enemy, which would over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm them with infamy all their days.</p>
            <p>The Grand Viſier's advice was to ſerve as a Law, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were forc'd to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply. In the mean while ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending leſt the <hi>Janiſaries</hi> ſhould joyn themſelves to thoſe who were for raiſing the ſiege, he took care to keep 'em within the bounds of their duty, and made 'em great promiſes, in caſe they behav'd themſelves well in the fight.
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:57262:62"/> The next morning he took a review of his Army, which conſiſted ſtill of an Hundred and Ten Thouſand fighting men, and reſolving to call to his aſſiſtance the Troops which he had left about <hi>Raab,</hi> and other places of <hi>Hungary,</hi> he ſent others in their places, in whom he put not ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence.</p>
            <p>On the ſide which the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians had reſolv'd to attack his lines, there ſtood a Wood, through which they muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily paſs to come at him. The Chriſtians at the begining of the Campagn took care to make a commodious paſſage. But the Grand Viſier believ'd he might annoy 'em, if he poſſeſt himſelf of it, he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon timely ſent five or ſix
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:57262:62"/> Battalions, who had fell'd ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Trees, with which they retrenched themſelves. On the other hand the Grand Viſier, having left 20 Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men for the Guard of his Camp and Trench, marcht out of his Trenches with his Horſe and Foot, whereof he form'd three lines, without reckoning the Body he had reſerv'd, and poſſeſſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of a little hill, which might be advantagious during the fight, he cauſed his Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non to be brought thither, charging thoſe who were pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced there above all things to abide firm.</p>
            <p>In the mean while the Chriſtian Army, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders of which had im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plor'd the divine aſſiſtance,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:57262:63"/> by publick and private Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, marched with great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of Victory, having at its head a Prince of ſo great reputation, and who had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready beaten the <hi>Turks</hi> in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other occaſions. But as this Circumſtance rais'd their Courage, ſo did it abaſe that of the <hi>Turks,</hi> who fear'd more the <hi>Poles</hi> than any Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſo that they had rather it had been the Emperor at the head of his Forces, than to have there a King, whoſe Fortune and Valour they great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dreaded. But beſides that the Emperor would not ſo greatly expoſe himſelf, the King of <hi>Poland</hi> came not ſo far to obey another, and the Emperor on his ſide would pretend to Command him,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:57262:63"/> and therefore t'avoid all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes he remain'd at <hi>Lintz,</hi> ordering Prayers to be ſaid in all the Churches, which were never empty of people, who ſought of God with the greateſt fervor, to favour the Chriſtian Army.</p>
            <p>The Army being arriv'd at the Wood, the fight began, and was at firſt ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>inately e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough maintain'd by both Parties. But the Chriſtians who ſaw that if they behav'd not themſelves fiercely in this occaſion, the Grand Viſier might refreſh his Troops which would give them far more trouble, leapt over the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenchments of the Enemy, and having driven them from the Wood, kill'd as many of 'em as were not quick enough
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:57262:64"/> to ſave themſelves. The Wood being wholly clear'd, the Avantguard of the Army drew up it ſelf at the head of the Wood, to ſave the arrear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard, fearing leſt marching farther, without being in a condition to fight, the Grand Viſier ſhould march up towards them, and make advantage of the ill condition wherein he might find them. But he was unwilling to depart ſo far from <hi>Vienna,</hi> fearing leſt while he was on the other ſide, the Chriſtians would let out the <hi>Danube</hi> over one part of his Army, and attack thoſe he had left for the keeping the lines, who would be too much put to it to reſiſt at the ſame time theſe new Enemies, and the Garriſon likewiſe,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:57262:64"/> who would not fail to ſally out.</p>
            <p>And therefore he every mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſent out Parties, to ſee what paſſed on the ſide of the <hi>Danube,</hi> for he was in greater fear of what might be done on that ſide, than on the other, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho he was advertiſed every moment that the Chriſtians march'd againſt him, &amp; ſhould have 'em upon his skirts with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in an hour or two at fartheſt.</p>
            <p>And indeed 'twas neceſſary theſe ſuccors ſhould be ſo near. For altho the <hi>Turks</hi> were not as yet in the Town, yet they were at leaſt under it by means of their mines, which was the reaſon why <hi>Starenberg</hi> caus'd a Lanthorn to be put on the high Tower of S. <hi>Stephen,</hi> which was the ſign, agreed upon by the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> and he,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:57262:65"/> when he ſhould find himſelf in a great ſtrait. His Miners alſo were ſo heartleſs, that he had all the difficulty in the World to make 'em work, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Garriſon were ſo dampt by their inceſſant labors and toils, and which is worſe reduced to 5 thouſand 5 hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred men, of 16 thouſand that they were in the beginning of the Siege. For if they loſt ſix thouſand by the hand of the Enemy, ſickneſs had carried away few leſs, ſo that dying as they did in heaps, they were not burried one by one, but thrown ten or twelve together in an hole.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that had eſcaped ſo great danger, and who in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of the ſame fortune, ſuffered themſelves almoſt to
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:57262:65"/> languiſh away, being informed that the ſuccors, with which they had been ſo often vainly flattered were near, and on this ſide the Wood, where they were ſeen already to appear, took their Arms with ſuch courage, that a man would have thought 'em other men, than thoſe one might have ſeen the other moment. They went all on the Rampart, without expecting any other command, than that which their courage inſpired, and it much availd <hi>Staremberg,</hi> that they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livened by this new hope, for thoſe whom the Grand Viſier left to guard the Camp, and ordered to go up to the aſſault, as ſoon as ever they ſaw him March towards the Enemy, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted themſelves with ſo
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:57262:66"/> great Reſolution and conſtancy that they never had before done the like. In the mean time the beſieged, who conſidered if they repelled this laſt effort, they ſhould be delivered from the miſery which had ſo long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted them, fought with no leſs courage; ſo that never was an hotter diſpute on both ſides.</p>
            <p>Whilſt this happened, the King of <hi>Poland</hi> was ingaged with the Grand Viſier, who had march'd up to him, with more courage than prudence. For without conſidering he left the Poſt, where he had lodged his Cannon, and whence he might greatly moleſt the Chriſtians, he began the charge, whereas he ſhould have expected the King of <hi>Poland</hi> to come and charge him. But whether he
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:57262:66"/> believed there was any advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to him that gave the firſt onſet, or would thereby ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate his men, of whoſe cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage he doubted, he neglected to uſe theſe precautions, of which he preſently repented. For his Troops giving back, after the firſt charge, the Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ians, ſo boldly purſued them, that thoſe that had the care of the Cannon durſt not fire, leſt it ſhould prove as hurtful to their own men as ours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Staremberg</hi> being advertized by perſons whom he had pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the higheſt parts of the Town, that the beginning of the combate was as favorable to the Chriſtians as could be deſired, made at the ſame time a Sally out of the Garriſon, who had already drove the
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:57262:67"/> 
               <hi>Turks</hi> from off the Rampart. And ſeveral Citizens being mixt with the Soldiers, to ſhare with 'em in the Honour, they all fiercely attackt the Enemy, who thought already of pack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up their baggage, from the advice which they had of the Grand <hi>Viſier,</hi> that all things went ill on his part, and that they ought to think of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat. Then every one with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out regretting what he had left in the Tent, minded only to ſave himſelf, when <hi>Staremberg</hi> at the head of his men charg'd them ſo vigorouſly, that they threw themſelves down one upon another for haſte, who ſhould firſt get away. And the lines of circumvallation hindring 'em from paſſing ſo ſoon as they deſired, they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavor'd
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:57262:67"/> to fill them up with their Muskets, which at that moment ſerved for Pick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>axes and Shovels, others with their hands; every one uſing more diligence to Ruin theſe lines than they had done to put 'em in the condition they were in. <hi>Staremberg</hi> ſeeing the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order wherein the <hi>Turks</hi> were, was raviſht at ſo happy an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion. But his prudence, hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring him from going far from the Town, he contented him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with ſending ſome Horſe after the hindermoſt, and ſtaid himſelf in the mean time near the Walls, where he cauſed the Enemies works to be demoliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, leſt things ſhould change its face.</p>
            <p>In the mean time theſe fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitives encreaſed the fear in the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:57262:68"/> 
               <hi>Viſiers</hi> Army, which was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready but two great; for the King of <hi>Poland</hi> had defeated his left Wing, whoſe Horſe left the foot at the diſcretion of the <hi>Poles,</hi> who had fallen upon 'em and put 'em to the Sword; as to the right Wing, it made a little more reſiſtance. But the Grand Viſier conſidering that in the condition wherein the fight was, it was impoſſible to reſtabliſh it, &amp; that moreover the Trench was quitted, with all the works which had coſt him ſo much blood, he reſolv'd to ſpare that which remain'd; and to leave rather his Camp, and his Tents which were ſtill ſtanding, than to be the cauſe of ſhedding more by a fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs obſtinacy. In this deſign he cauſed the Retreat to be
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:57262:68"/> ſounded, but the foot being not able to follow the Horſe, which rather fled than held on an orderly <hi>March,</hi> ſeveral of 'em were cut in pieces, and there were not a 4th part of 'em ſaved.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>Poland</hi> having made a Detachment, to put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Town, and given thanks to God for his Victory, in the very Field where he gained it, gave ſtrict command, under grievous penalties, that no one ſhould leave his rank to plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. The Dukes of <hi>Bavaria, Saxony,</hi> and <hi>Lorrain,</hi> who had fought likewiſe with a great deal of courage, did as much on their ſide, and the keeping of the <hi>Turks</hi> Camp was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to three thouſand men, whilſt a Council of War was
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:57262:69"/> call'd to know whether the Enemy, ſhould be purſued, or they reſt contented with the advantage already obtained. The advices were different, thereupon the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> with all thoſe that were in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors intereſts, were for pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing their Victory, but the Dukes of <hi>Saxony</hi> and <hi>Bavaria,</hi> who came only to ſuccour <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enna,</hi> would not any more hazard their Troops. Eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> who complained, that by reaſon of his Religion, they had been made to ſuffer enough all ready. In effect the beſt quarters were not his, and he had heard that they ſuſpected leſt his Troops having their Winter quarters in <hi>Hungary,</hi> ſhould hold intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:57262:69"/> with <hi>Teckely.</hi> This Prince ſeeing then, that after he had traverſt a great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, hazarded his reputation, and even his life, and left his Eſtates, to ſuccour thoſe of another, he was ſo ill recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed, reſolved upon return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing home, where he arrived more laden with glory than ſpoil; for the confederates ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he forſook the common cauſe notwithſtanding their opinion, gave him what part they pleaſed; which again doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his diſcontent.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi> had better uſage, becauſe perhaps the Emperor apprehended, leſt he in the differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences he had with <hi>France,</hi> ſhould take part againſt him being moreover ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licited to it by ſeveral advantageous offers, beſides his Aliance with it. Howſoever all theſe Princes being not agreed, they made, as we ſay,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:57262:70" rendition="simple:additions"/> a Golden bridge, for the Enemy to paſs over, who retired on the I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le of <hi>Newhauſel,</hi> where they expected 3 days the wracks of their Army. In the mean while the Grand Viſier was not without inquietude, how the grand <hi>Seignor</hi> would receive the news of his defeat, and to caſt all the fault on others, he wrote a Letter againſt thoſe that had the chief com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand under him. But we have not heard what the Grand <hi>Seignor</hi> has reſolved thereupon, no more than what the King of <hi>Poland</hi> has done, reports concerning whom are ſo various, that ther's as yet no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tianty of 'em. Yet tis not to be doubted being ſo great a Captain as he is, but he will make the beſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of his Victory, which all Chriſtians ought to deſire.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:57262:70" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
